A Guide to the R. Buckminster Fuller Collection, 1949-1978
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
R. Buckminster Fuller Collection, 1949-1978
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1975-007
1 box, 1 flat box; 0.4 cu. ft.
R. Buckminster Fuller (1895-1983) was a poet, philosopher, inventor, engineer and architect. Fuller, or "Bucky" to his friends and colleagues, was most well known for his invention of the geodesic dome, a ground-based dome with no limiting dimensions. The collection contains unsigned correspondence by Fuller and others, as well as various articles on architecture and the geodesic dome, nature, utopian design, space and science.
The R. Buckminster Fuller Archives, Philadelphia, PA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The R. Buckminster Fuller Collection was purchased for the architectural collection of the library around 1975.
Biographical Information
R. Buckminster Fuller was born in Milton, Massachusetts on July 12, 1895. He attended Harvard University from 1913-15, but never finished his degree. He attended the U.S. Naval Academy in 1917 and served as an officer in the U.S. Navy during World War I. In 1954, Fuller patented the geodesic dome, the structure he is most famous for as an architect. The U.S. Pavilion, a geodesic dome designed by Fuller, was a main feature of the Canadian Universal and International Exhibition in 1967. Fuller was also the inventor of a "dymaxion" car as well as a "dymaxion" world map, a map which limited the distortions that are common with most world maps. Fuller was not just an inventor and architect, but also a philosopher and poet. He published many books and articles throughout his life, both fiction and non-fiction. Fuller's contributions as a poet, philosopher, architect and inventor have made him the subject of numerous books and articles, as well as earning him many honorary degrees and awards.
Scope and Content
The R. Buckminster Fuller Collection consists of correspondence written by Fuller himself as well as letters written to him from various sources. Correspondence consists of unsigned copies of letters to and from Fuller; most pertain to the operation of his business, Geodesics, Inc. In addition, there are numerous reprints of newspaper, magazine, and scholarly journal articles written about Fuller's architecture and achievements. Also included are many examples of Fuller's own writing, including a reprint of a portion of his book, Nine Chains to the Moon.
Arrangement
The R. Buckminster Fuller Collection is arranged in three series and in complete chronological order within each series. Some items are stored separately in a flat box (Box 2) due to their large size.
Series I contains correspondence of Fuller and others pertaining to various subjects, such as the running of his business Geodesics, Inc.
Series II contains four folders consisting of the writings of Fuller. These writings include poems, articles, and stories written by Fuller throughout his life.
Series III contains seven folders consisting of articles and other materials written about the life and works of Fuller.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Buckminster Fuller's complete archive was acquired by Stanford University in 1999. Some of the resources have been placed online.
Contents List
- Letters to and from R. Buckminster Fuller
  - Nov 1953 - Dec 1962 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Writings of R. Buckminster Fuller
  - 1952-1965 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Sep 1965 - Aug 1969 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Oct 1969 - May 1976 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - 1974 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Writings about R. Buckminster Fuller
  - Jun 1949 - Jan 1959 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - May 1959 - April 1965 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Apr 1965 - 1969 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Nov 1969 - Dec 1973 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - c. 1975 - Mar 1976 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Honorary Doctorate Citations, 1954 - c. 1975 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - 1955-1967 (Box-folder 2:2)